Today's דף *Daf* is דף למד *Daf Lamed*. We start actually ahead
on the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* on דף למד *Daf Lamed* near the
bottom of the page. And we are now moving up to the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* actually on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur*. It is daybreak and we know שחיטה *Shechitah* is going
to be coming up, but the first thing they did is they
had him go to the מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah*. We were told as
a general reason people would go to the מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah* after
defecating and they would wash their hands and feet after urinating, but
we do not yet know why the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol* is going to the מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah* the morning of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*. So let's take a look at the
next משנה *Mishna* on למד *Lamed*. אין אדם נכנס לעזרה *Ein adam
nichnas l’azarah*. As I have been pointing out, we are constantly referring
as we try to move forward and talking about the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, we are constantly stepping back and referring to
what would be the normal
case in the normal way the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*
would operate. So now we say as well, אין אדם נכנס לעזרה
לעבודה *Ein adam nichnas l’azarah l’avodah*. A person cannot enter into the
עזרה Azarah *Azarah*, the courtyard, which is שער ניקנור *Sha'ar Nikanor*, which
is where even ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* can go and not yet into
the היכל Heichal, *Heichal*, the covered building, the open courtyard where the
מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbe’ach* was. A person cannot enter into that space to
do the service אפילו טהור tahor. *afillu tahor*, even if you are
pure, עד שיטבול *ad sheyitbol*, you have to do a ritual immersion
before you enter into that space. And that is presumably why the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* who has been spending the week
becoming טהור tahor, *tahor* does a ritual immersion in the morning as
well. חמש טבילות tevilas? ועשר קידושין טובל tovel, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
ומקדש בו ביום *Chamesh tevilot v’asar kiddushin tovel Kohen Gadol umekadesh bo
bayom*. The five immersions and ten washing of the hands and feet,
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* immerses and is מקדש Mikdash
*mekadesh* and sanctifies the hands and feet on that day. So he
basically goes to the מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah* five times on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* and washes his hands and feet ten times. Each time
he goes to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*, he washes his hands and
feet before and after, and we will spell out exactly when that
is and why that is in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. וכולן בקודש
*V’chulan bakodesh*, all of them were done in the עזרה Azarah *Azarah*,
על בית הפרוה *al beit haparva*, on the top of the בית
הפרוה *Beit Haparva*, which we had learned before
was one of the rooms in which the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
*Kohen Gadol* was there sort of prepared, חוץ מזו בלבד bilvad. *chutz
mizo bilvad*, with the exception of the first one
because in order to enter the עזרה Azarah, *Azarah* you have to
do what? Right, exactly. Thank you very much.
Just making sure we are paying attention and you are listening. All
right. פירסו סדין של בוץ בינו לבין העם *Pirsu sadin shel butz
beino l’vein ha’am*. They spread a linen curtain they held up, spread
vertically, a linen curtain to separate between him and the people.
And then there is a question, what did he do? Presumably then
he went to the מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah*, but the next line is
וקידש ידיו ורגליו *vekadesh yadav v’raglav*, question if that is in the
גירסא *girsah*, we will see about that. But they spread a curtain.
So presumably where he was going in the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* was
somehow visible,
it was on the rooftop and it was somehow visible, so they
had to protect his privacy so they held up a curtain while
he was going to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*. שאלו את בן זומא
Ben Zoma, *Sha'alu et Ben Zoma*. They asked בן זומא Ben Zoma
*Ben Zoma*, טבילה tevilah. זו למה *Tevilah zu lamah*? What is the
purpose for this טבילה tevilah. *tevilah*? Not the טבילה tevilah, *tevilah* of
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, again we are still in
the context of the regular year, but the טבילה tevilah *tevilah* that
a normal person would do when he would enter into the עזרה
Azarah. *Azarah*. אמר להם *Amar lahem*, so he said to them: ומה
המשנה מקודש לקודש וממקום שאין ענוש כרת kares למקום שענוש כרת kares
*Uma hamishaneh mikodesh l’kodesh umimakon she’enosh karet l’makom she’enosh karet*. Because look,
it says very often by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, now it is
going to be interesting because now יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, we are
always sort of talking about the regular year and they would do
which of those components would they do also on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. But here we are working in the reverse. We are going
to use the עבודה avodah, *avodah* of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and
what the תורה Torah *Torah* describes as the עבודה avodah, *avodah* of
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* to teach me a rule for the rest
of the year. And what does the תורה Torah *Torah* describe by
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? Very often in אחרי מות *Acharei Mot*, which
describes what אהרן *Aharon* does, it says right: ורחץ במים את בשרו
ולבשם *vrachatz bamayim et besaro v’lavasham*, ורחץ במים *vrachatz bamayim*,
that he is constantly refers to him immersing himself and putting on
the garments. And we are going to see that the basic rule
is that we learn from the פסוקים *pesukim* is that every time
he switches from the work, the עבודה avodah *avodah*, the service he
is doing in the inner sanctum, in the היכל Heichal *Heichal*, the
covered space, the space that has the שלחן *Shulchan* and the מנורה
*Menorah*, that is where he wears the garments of only white linen,
the four simple garments of white linen. When he does the עבודה
avodah. *avodah* on the outside, he is wearing the garments of gold.
It is also not just where he is doing it, but also
what type of עבודה avodah. *avodah*. Is it the unique עבודה avodah?
*avodah* of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, is it the regular עבודה avodah
*avodah* of the rest of the year? But when he moves back
from one to the other, one space to the other and one
עבודה avodah, *avodah* to the other, he switches from the white garments
to the gold garments, from the four garments to the eight. And
each time he does that switch, he immerses himself. So here בן
זומא Ben Zoma, *Ben Zoma* is going to say a קל וחומר
*kal vachomer*. If you are going to immerse yourself when you are
already in the עזרה Azarah *Azarah*, when you are just switching from
one sanctified space to another sanctified space, and you have already immersed
yourself before and you still have to immerse yourself, so how much
more so when you are making a transition... from outside the מקדש
Mikdash into the מקדש Mikdash, that it requires a טבילה. tevilah. ומה
משנה מקודש לקודש, uma meshaneh mikodesh lekodesh,
from a sanctified space to a sanctified space, במקום שאינו כרת, bimkom
she’eino kares, from a place in which you get כרת kares if
you enter in when you are טמא, tamei, like the עזרה Azarah
or the היכל, Heichal למקום שאינו כרת limkom she’eino kares to another
space which has the same consequences, all of those cases טעון טבילה,
ta'un tevilah, you have to immerse yourself. המשנה מחול לקודש hameshaneh mechol
lekodesh וממקום שאינו כרת למקום שיש כרת, umimkom she’eino kares limkom sheyesh
kares,
if you’re switching from unsanctified space to sanctified space, and from space
that you do not get כרת for if you are טמא tamei
to space that you do get כרת for, אינו דין שטעון טבילה?
eino din sheta’un tevilah? How much more so would you have to
be—would you have to immerse yourself? So he said we learn it
out from what goes on by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol that
a transition from one space to another, you know, and all the
more so from חול chol to קודש, kodesh, demands טבילה. tevilah, Now
of course, we don't learn everything out from the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol because in a normal year, if a כהן Kohen had to
go from the עזרה Azarah, into the היכל Heichal. or the היכל
Heichal to the עזרה, Azarah he would not do a טבילה, tevilah,
right? So this idea of within the מקדש Mikdash? changing of spaces
does טבילה tevilah is not something we generally apply, but certainly to
minimally learn out from that, that the transition into it, that the
idea of moving into a space is considered—requires something of a טבילה.
tevilah, One minute, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says, סרך טבילה היא זו, serach tevilah hee zo, this is
really some remnant of a טבילה, tevilah some vestige, I mean that’s
not exactly the right word, but it means it’s not really a
demanded טבילה, tevilah it's just a
pseudo-טבילה—maybe tevilah that’s not the precise
word—כדי שיזכור טומאה ישנה שבידו ויפרוש, k'dei sheyizkor tumah yeshanah shebeyado veyifrosh,
because if you go to the מקוה, mikvah right? When you go
to the מקוה, mikvah what’s the thing you’ll immediately think about? You
think about am I טמא? tamei? I'm going to the מקוה, mikvah
normally it’s in order to become pure. So it evokes that question
of am I טמא tamei and it makes you reflect more than
just a question, we just say, one minute, before you enter into
the מקדש, Mikdash. take a minute to think if you became טמא
tamei during the week. Nah, I didn’t. Okay fine, go in. But
if we actually make you go into the מקוה, mikvah you're going
to stop and think about oh my gosh, that's right, I've got
to be טהור. tahor One minute, I actually touched something. Now sometimes
a lot of things you did, the מקוה mikvah will clear up,
except if actually you did touch a—thing,
even after going to the מקוה, mikvah you have to wait till
nightfall. So if you're going to the מקוה mikvah, and you're—oh my
gosh, that's right, I did touch that שרץ. sheretz. So then you're
going to turn around and not go to the מקוה mikvah today,
you have to wait till nightfall. And sometimes you’ll remember some things
that require seven days. You became a זב, zav, a woman was
a נדה. niddah. So going to the מקוה mikvah. is going to
experientially make you sort of confront this question and think about am
I really טהור, tahor am I really ready to go into the
מקדש? Mikdash, And that's why we do it, but it’s really a
rabbinic concern, it is not really required, and again, not only is
it not really required, it doesn't—if you were טמא, tamei, it wouldn't
fully solve the problem because you would not be fully טהור tahor
then even after going into the מקוה mikvah until nightfall. So one
is doing it more for a ritual purpose, and the other is
for סרך טומאה, serach tumah, neither are doing it for a real
טומאה tumah because then it would not really solve the problem. I
want to just point out that this to some degree parallels the
whole question of the seven-day preparation that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
would do
before יום—before—before, you know, יום כיפור. Does anybody remember the two basic
reasons we gave for the seven-day preparation? Michael?
Either because you want to—basically give him more of a מעלה ma’alah
of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or הר סיני Har Sinai model.
Well right, there’s a הר סיני Har Sinai model, and then there’s
the model of the מלואים, miluim, right? Of the מלואים. miluim. So,
now those are neither of those are exactly the טהרה taharah model,
both of those are certain preparation in a way. One is more
preparation of the עבודה, avodah. the other is preparation of the encounter
with God. And then there was a third thing that came up
after that whole two framing, which all spoke about the שבע ימים
sheva yamim because—because you have to be מטהר metaher him, right? And
that’s why you sprinkle on all the days because you want to
do it בזמנו, bizmano, right? Remember all of that discussion? So there
were those two models which are different forms of preparation, and then
there was this like סרך טומאה serach tumah model, maybe he’s טמא
tamei and let’s do all this type of stuff. So interestingly, that
then becomes a similar question about a normal person that enters the
מקדש. Mikdash, A normal person that enters the מקדש, Mikdash, either something
that sort of like prepares you for that event, a ritual טבילה,
tevilah you’re about to make that transition, right? Or no, it’s just
the טומאה tumah טהרה taharah types of concerns. We’re not definitely טמא,
tamei, then we’d actually have differently, but a way of being sensitive
about that. So I think that’s quite fascinating that this almost one
moment of טבילה tevilah parallels two basic approaches to the כהן גדול’s
Kohen Gadol seven-day preparation as well. Okay, so that’s where—these two ways
of reading it. תוספות Tosafot by the way points out that if
we assume it’s biblical, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, ומה משנה
בין קודש לקודש, uma meshaneh bein kodesh lekodesh, תוספות Tosafot says תימה
לי, teima lei, איכא למיפרך ika lemirach מה להלן שכן רוצה לעבוד
עבודה. ma lehallan sheken rotzeh la’avod avodah. By the כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol he’s going to the טבילה tevilah because he’s about to do
the עבודה, avodah he’s not just moving into a space. אבל טהור
נכנס שלא לעבוד מנין? aval tahor nichnas shelo la’avod minayin? ויש לומר
דהאי דבר הקל וחומר אינו אלא בטהור נכנס כדי לעבוד. veyesh lomar
dehai devar hakal v'chomer eino ela betahor nichnas k'dei la’avod.
אבל מדרבנן גזרו אפילו בנכנס שלא לעבוד. aval mi'derabbanan gazru afilu benichnas
shelo la’avod. So תוספות Tosafot wants to say even assuming that there’s
this biblical model that you need to go... To the מקווה mikvah
before entering into the מקדש, Mikdash. that is only in order to
do the עבודה avodah of entering into the מקדש, Mikdash, not just
entering into the space of the מקדש. Mikdash, Okay? That would be
Rabbinic. The Biblical idea would be doing the עבודה. avodah And again,
these two approaches now parallel what Michael said, the two approaches of
the מילואים Miluim versus הר סיני. Har Sinai. The הר סיני Har
Sinai idea of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was the just entering
into that space, the encounter, the presence in that space, whereas the
מילואים Miluim model was preparing for the עבודה. avodah So quite fascinatingly
you have all three possibilities that came up by the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol for the seven day preparation that I think implicitly being
echoed here. It's a טומאה tumah concern, it's a type of a
ritual preparation to enter into the space, not a טומאה tumah concern,
and within there you have two questions. Is it to enter into
the space or to enter into the עבודה? avodah So that's my
little חידוש chiddush here that these three things have a very nice
parallel to the seven day preparation. All right, so now let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara All right,
פירוש, peirush, במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamiflegi? Now what do they debate? Doesn't
really mean what do they debate? It means what would be a
practical consequence of their debate? So top of ל' עמוד ב', Lamed
Amud Beis, באחולי עבודה קמיפלגי, be'achulei avodah kamiflegi, whether if you did
not do the immersion would the service be desecrated? Would you be
would
meaning would you actually would your עבודה avodah be invalidated if you
did not do the immersion?
בן זומא, Ben Zoma. בן זומא Ben Zoma, that learns it out
from the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol so it's a real biblical demand
and a ritual demand, מחיל עבודה, mechil avodah, so it would desecrate
from the word חולין, chullin, it would desecrate the עבודה, avodah it
would invalidate the עבודה. avodah ליהודה, Le-Yehudah, לא מחיל עבודה lo mechil
avodah according to Rebbe Yehudah it would not. So the גמרא Gemara
says because that's only a Rabbinic concern just to make you remember.
ולבן זומא מי מחיל, U-le-Ben Zoma mi mechil, would it really would
it really invalidate, desecrate the עבודה avodah according to Ben Zoma? והתניא,
Ve-hatanya, we learned in a בריתא, Beraisa, what would be if the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol did not do one of his טבילות? tevilas
What would be the story then? כהן גדול שלא טבל ולא קידש,
Kohen Gadol shelo taval velo kidesh, if a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
did not do a טבילה tevillah and did not wash his hands
when he was supposed to,
and we're talking about like even between later,
yeah, any of the עבודות avodos which is exactly even the ones
which which were the model for this, בין בגד לבגד ובין עבודה
לעבודה, bein beged le-beged u-vein avodah le-avodah, from the white garments to
the gold or vice versa or between different types of services, outer
services and inner services, עבודתו כשירה, avodato kesherah, בדיעבד bedi'avad his עבודה
avodah is kosher. אחד כהן גדול ואחד כהן הדיוט, Echad Kohen Gadol
ve-echad Kohen Hedyot, whether the normal כהן Kohen or whether
a whether the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור or whether
a normal כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. Now, that's if you did not
do
the טבילה tevillah when you are changing from your weekday clothes to
your to your holy clothes or you're not do the טבילה tevillah
when you are changing כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is changing from the
white to the gold and so on, בדיעבד bedi'avad it's okay. Now,
what's important to point out is שלא קידש ידיו ורגליו בשחרית ועבד
עבודתו פסולה. shelo kidesh yadav ve-raglav be-shacharis ve-avad avodato pesulah. So
actually I think I put the period in the wrong place before.
So first of all is בין עבודה לעבודה עבודתו כשירה, bein avodah
le-avodah avodato kesherah, period. Okay, so a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who
doesn't do the טבילות tevilas בדיעבד bedi'avad the עבודה avodah is kosher.
אחד כהן גדול ואחד כהן הדיוט, Echad Kohen Gadol ve-echad Kohen Hedyot,
however, whether it's a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, or כהן הדיוט Kohen
Hedyot שלא קידש ידיו ורגליו שחרית shelo kidesh yadav ve-raglav shacharis that
did not do the initial washing of hands in the beginning of
the day in that
case ועבד עבודתו פסולה ve-avad avodato pesulah it is invalid. Because it's
worth pointing out, yes, what's worth pointing out is with all of
these טבילות and all this washing of the hands and we all
discussed yesterday you wash your hands because you urinate and all this,
there is one act that is absolutely biblically required and that is
the קידוש ידיים ורגליים kiddush yadayim ve-raglayim in the beginning of the
day. The תורה Torah, says when it speaks about making the כיור,
kiyor, right, ועשית כיור נחשת, ve-asita kiyor nechoshet, right, ואת כנו נחשת,
ve-et kano nechoshet, right, ונתת אותו בין אהל מועד ובין המזבח ונתת
שמה מים ורחצו ממנו אהרן ובניו את ידיהם ואת רגליהם בבואם אל
אהל מועד או בגשתם אל המזבח לשרת, ve-natata oto bein ohel moed
u-vein ha-mizbe'ach ve-natata shama mayim ve-rachatsu mimeno Aharon u-vanav et yadeihem ve-et
ragleihem be-vo'am el ohel moed o be-gishtam el ha-mizbe'ach le-shareis, right, ולא
ימותו. velo yamutu. Is that the end of the פסוק? pasuk? ורחצו
ידיהם ורגליהם ולא ימותו. ve-rachatsu yadeihem ve-ragleihem velo yamutu. Okay, thanks. So
anyway, so there it says that if they're when you're
you know you have to wash your hands before entering in to
the אהל מועד Ohel Moed or before doing the עבודה avodah and
if you don't you're חייב מיתה. chayav misah. So if you're חייב
מיתה chayav misah obviously it's pretty serious consequence and another גמרא Gemara
learns out that if you didn't wash your hands at the beginning
of the day the עבודה avodah. is invalid. So that's the one
thing that everybody can agree is biblical, is חייב מיתה, chayav misah,
if you don't do it the עבודה avodah. is invalid. That's the
washing of the hands at the beginning of the day. It is
not the need to go to the מקווה mikvah before you enter
into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That is not the need for
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to go to the מקווה mikvah between
the garments or to wash his hands between the garments. All of
that is not the fundamental washing of the hands in the beginning
of the day. So if you don't do that washing of hands
חייב מיתה chayav misah and the עבודה avodah, is invalid. But if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol fails to do the טבילה between the
garments or the washing of the hands between the garments בדיעבד bedi'avad
it's okay and the argument therefore is if you use בן זומא'ס
Ben Zoma's model of any normal person who goes to the מקווה
mikvah at the beginning of the day is learned from the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol then if that's true how can you say בדיעבד
bedi'avad it's no good, even the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. בדיעבד bedi'avad
it's good if he did
not. So yes, that's an interesting question.
So were they there day—so it's actually quite interesting, and I hadn't
thought to make this third connection, but the exact two models here
about why would you go into the מקוה mikvah at the beginning
of the day, there's a מחלוקת ראשונים machloket Rishonim what the basic
reason is for the תקנה takkanah of washing your hands at the
beginning of the day.
The רשב״א Rashba I believe is the one that says that it's,
you know, maybe in the middle of the night you touch parts
of your body and you have to have your hands clean for
דאווענען, davening, which parallels the סרך טומאה serach tumah reason. Whereas the
ר״אש Rosh says, no, because the same way the כהן Kohen would
wash his hands to begin the עבודה in the מקדש, Mikdash, our
עבודה in the larger world begins at the day, we wash our
hands to begin our עבודת השם avodat Hashem in the larger world,
which is a very beautiful idea to think about that transference of
the עבודה that was done, the ritual עבודה in the מקדש, Mikdash
how it now transfers to our activities in the larger world. But
that exactly parallels, if you think about it, the two explanations of
why you would go to the מקוה mikvah before entering as well.
Yes, that's—but that's a separate reason, that's not part of the fundamental
תקנה, takkanah, okay, that's not why they made the ברכה bracha and
the whole thing. Okay, so anyway, so thank you for that, very
nice, all these three things line up. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says, look, even if כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, is your model, when
we're not talking about the basic washing of hands first thing before
entering the מקדש, Mikdash even the כהן Kohen גדול model בדיעבד bedi'avad
it's okay. So what difference is it going to make whether your
model is the כהן Kohen גדול model or whether it's a סרך
טומאה serach tumah model? Okay, you can't say the נפקא מינה nafka
mina is whether בדיעבד bedi'avad it's not good, because clearly בדיעבד bedi'avad
it would be okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא למיקם בעשה
קמיפלגי. ella lemakam be'aseh kamiflagi.
So the first נפקא מינה nafka mina is whether you've transgressed a
biblical positive מצוה, mitzvah, not a negative one, but a positive one.
According to בן זומא, Ben Zoma, קאי בעשה, ka'i be'aseh, the same
way the כהן Kohen גדול, the תורה Torah says you have to
go to the מקוה mikvah. when you're changing your clothes, and if
he doesn't, he violated that demand in the תורה, Torah so he
violated
a תורה demand. And according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, לא קאי
בעשה, lo ka'i be'aseh, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah he did
not violate a תורה demand. Okay, so that doesn't really, you know,
that's in terms of their
שכר ועונש, sachar ve'onesh, but it's a דרבנן. de-rabbanan. So he violated
a rabbinic command, a rabbinic requirement. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
has not spelled out an actual practical נפקא מינה. nafka mina. It's
only spelled out basically it's another way of saying according to one
it's biblical, according to the other it's rabbinic. Okay, that's the basic
difference that's said so far, we don't yet have the practical difference,
but hold on, we're going to get to some practical differences. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומי אית ליה לרבי יהודה
האי סברא? u-mi it lei le-Rabbi Yehudah hai sevara? Does רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah really hold of this reason that the whole reason is
because maybe you're טמא tamei and just to make you remember? והתניא,
ve-hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, מצורע. metzora. Now a מצורע
metzora went through a seven-day purification process, right? And then on the
eighth—as on the seventh day there was all this thing about the
sprinkling and the whatever and he goes to the מקוה Mikveh and
the whole thing on the seventh day and that sort of finishes
the purification process. The next morning he enters—right, because he's a טבול
יום tvul yom and he doesn't fully become pure until that night
of the seventh day. And then the next morning he enters into
the מקדש Mikdash. and he brings a קרבן, korban, and that's completely
finishes it. And any person by the way who has to bring
a קרבן korban at the end of a purification process like a
זב zav is another example and so on, or a זבה. zavah.
That eighth day of bringing the קרבן, korban, until he brings it
he's called מחוסר כיפורים, mechussar kippurim, lacking the full atonement or the
fullest full purification. So on the seventh day he does his purification
process, he goes to the מקוה, Mikveh, at the night he's a
טבול יום, tvul yom, now it's the night, he's no longer a
טבול יום, tvul yom, but he's מחוסר כיפורים, mechussar kippurim, he brings
his קרבן korban on day eight and then he's fully pure. Okay,
now let's talk, so now he comes to the מקדש Mikdash on
day eight. Does he have to go to the מקוה Mikveh, the
morning of day eight? What do you guys say?
Oh, that's a good question because he would have gone the previous
night.
He's been spending the last seven days becoming טהור tahor, and he
went to the מקוה. Mikveh. So does he have to? Maybe it
depends on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah and בן זומא. According to בן
זומא, anybody has to, I don't care how טהור Tahor you are,
it's a ritual requirement before the מקדש. Mikdash, But according to רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, right, if it's only in order to make you
remember that you might have been טמא, tamei, hey, I've been working
seven days of becoming טהור, Tahor. I don't need an extra reminder
and I just went to the מקוה Mikveh yesterday, I don't need
an extra thing to remind me. All right, well let's take a
look.
Let's look, one minute, let's take a look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, Baraita, מצורע שטובל ועומד בשער ניקנור. metzora she-tovel ve-omed
be-Sha'ar Nikanor. The מצורע metzora is the morning of the eighth, goes
to the מקוה Mikveh and then stands in the Gate of Nikanor,
which is the gate of entering into the עזרה. He doesn't yet
enter the עזרה because he's מחוסר כיפורים. mechussar kippurim. But he has
to be standing there because one of the things that's done with
the sacrifice is blood that's put on his thumbs, so he has
to stick his thumbs in, but he himself is not allowed in.
What? Yeah. Okay, so anyway... רבי יהודה אומר אינו צריך
טבילה שכבר טבל מאמש. Rabbi Yehudah omer eino tzarich tevilah she-kevar taval
me-emash. Rabbi Yehudah says he doesn't have to go to the מקוה
Mikveh because he did it the night before. Now what now the
גמרא Gemara is saying so you see רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah doesn't
require you to go to the מקוה. Mikveh Now of course it's
a crazy question. because he does require you to go to the
מקווה. mikvah. The only reason here he doesn't is because you took
care of it beforehand and that's exactly consistent with his reason. His
whole reason is you don't always, it's not a strict requirement, it's
to make you remember that you might be טמא. tamei. So here
it's not necessary. So the גמרא Gemara says that. So the גמרא
Gemara says האי כדתני תנא. hai kidtani tana. What do you mean
he doesn't require it there? That's because of the reason he said,
שכבר טבל מבעוד יום. shek'var taval miba'od yom. He went to the
מקווה mikvah the night before. Actually, that exactly fits Reb Yehuda's reason,
that it's not a strict ritual requirement and therefore since you already
went the day before you don't have to go now. So the
גמרא Gemara says דקארי לה מאי קארי לה? d'kari lah mai kari
lah? So yeah, that's a good point. What were you even thinking
to ask a question from there? If anything that completely supports, that's
completely consistent with Reb Yehuda's position. So the גמרא Gemara says משום
דקבעי למימר אחריתי עליה mishum d'ka'ba'ei l'meimar achriti aleih because really that
was just a lead up to another question which we had again
about the מצורעים metzoraim which was a problem for Reb Yehuda and
we'll see what that is in a minute. Charlie you had a
question?
Yeah, when the כהן goes to מקווה mikvah in the morning can
he do it before dawn?
That's a good question. It doesn't sound like it because it sounds
like they waited
for the ברקאי barkai and then they took him to the מקווה.
mikvah. And again you want to sort of go to the מקווה
mikvah in the immediate context of entering in and since the whole
עבודה begins in the day, it sounded like no you have to
wait till the morning.
דקארי D'kari is a לשון lashon of הוראה? hora'ah?
No,
Rashi seems to say the word משעוסק mishe'osek במתניתין זו, b'matnitin zo,
right? למה נתעסק? lama nit'asek? Why is the fact that you were
involved in this? Like כי קארי, ki ka'ari, like if it chances,
I'm not exactly sure what the etymology is. Why were you even
dealing with this question? What were you thinking about to be dealing
with this question?
So the א aleph there was a vowel.
I think, you'd have to ask Gasto, I don't know the etymology.
What about workers going to the
מקווה? mikvah? Yeah, anybody who wants to, any ישראל who wants to
enter the מקדש Mikdash has to go to the
מקווה. mikvah. Okay? So that's exactly it, it's not limited to a
כהן doing the עבודה. Okay so let's take a look. Right now
of course this is Tosafos's point because if you're learning it from
the כהן גדול on יום כיפור, you might think no it is
about a כהן doing the עבודה. It's not just about a normal
person just stepping in. So that's why תוספות Tosafos says yeah okay
maybe biblically based on the כהן גדול it would be based on
עבודה, but at least rabbinically we would extend it to anybody who
goes in and again we would make it a formal ritual requirement.
Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay so that was really a lead up to the next question.
Here's the next question. לשכת מצורעים, Lishkat Metzoraim, you might remember this
because we quoted this משנה before when we had all that discussion
of the layout of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash So there was
the chamber of the מצורעים. metzoraim. ששם מצורעים טובלים. shesham metzoraim tovlin.
That's where the מצורעים metzoraim would go to the מקווה mikvah because
that's consistent with the idea that a מצורע metzora would always go
to the מקווה mikvah on day eight. רבי יהודה אומר Rebbi Yehuda
omer לא מצורעים בלבד אמרו lo metzoraim bilvad amru אלא כל אדם.
ela kol adam.
Not only מצורעים metzoraim but any person would use it to go
to the מקווה. mikvah. That's fine because we learned before that people
go to the מקווה, mikvah, everybody goes to the מקווה. mikvah. So
what's the question? The question is that he says not only מצורעים.
metzoraim. So according to Reb Yehuda what do you mean not only
מצורעים, metzoraim, meaning מצורעים metzoraim would go? But why would מצורעים metzoraim
have to go to the מקווה, mikvah, didn't they go the day
before? And according to him that should be enough because the whole
point is to remember you were
טמא. tamei. Did they go into that room? No because yeah so
the גמרא's Gemara going to actually suggest that, but let's take a
look. Good, good try. So the גמרא Gemara says okay so לא
קשיא, lo kashya, הא דטבל הא דלא טבל. ha d'taval ha d'lo
taval.
So the מצורעים metzoraim would go in that מקווה mikvah if they
hadn't gone to the מקווה mikvah the day before. Right, okay, so
you hadn't gone, so then they would go into that room, but
if you'd gone the day before you wouldn't. The גמרא Gemara says
one minute, אי דלא טבל הערב שמש בעי. ei d'lo taval he'erev
shemesh ba'ei. First of all if you're really still טמא, tamei, you
didn't go on day seven to the מקווה, mikvah, and you're going
there, so that room, even though that room is in the הר
הבית, Har Habayis, it's not in whatever, you know it's not in
the עזרה itself, but nevertheless you're still טמא tamei and even after
you go to the מקווה mikvah you still need it to be
הערב שמש. he'erev shemesh. So how can you be there without having
gone to the מקווה mikvah the day before? You have to go
to the מקווה mikvah the day before, wait for it to be
הערב שמש, he'erev shemesh, and only as a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim
can you enter into הר הבית, Har Habayis, right?
Because you remember,
right here's your מקדש, Mikdash, right?
Here's your עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim with one of these is the
לשכת מצורעים. Lishkat Metzoraim. It's all on הר הבית. Har Habayis. Okay,
and this is your עזרה, right? And this is your היכל. Heichal.
Okay? So the כהן גדול would be moving from היכל to the
עזרה back and forth. The פסוק pasuk says you wash your hand
when you come to the, when you want to serve, when you
approach the מזבח לשרת l'shareit or when you're entering into the אהל
מועד Ohel Moed which would be the היכל. Okay, and this would
be... the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, which only had the sanctity of
הר הבית Har HaBayis but rabbinically it had more sanctity. Okay, so
if you are a מחוסר כפורים, Mechussar Kippurim,
you're looking at the מצורע Metzora on day eight, you're allowed to
stand here and stick your fingers in, but basically you can't go
into here. Okay, but a מחוסר כפורים, Mechussar Kippurim, somebody who has
not yet brought his קרבן, Korban, can go here to the עזרת
נשים. Ezras Nashim. I hope so because he's got to bring his
קרבן. Korban. So he might not be able to step in, but
he's allowed here. That you're allowed. Okay, but if you're a טבול
יום, Tvul Yom, somebody who's gone to the מקוה Mikveh but it's
not yet nightfall, you're allowed on הר הבית, Har HaBayis, but you
are not allowed in the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. And that's rabbinic,
so that's rabbinic. So if you've gone to the מקוה, Mikveh if
this guy on day seven has gone to the מקוה, Mikveh okay,
he can't even get into the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim until day
eight. No, no, no, טבול יום, Tvul Yom, no. If you're not
even a טבול יום, Tvul Yom, if you're really טמא, Tamei, then
you certainly can't go. You can't go on הר הבית. Har HaBayis.
What?
You can't go on הר הבית Har HaBayis if you're not even
a טבול יום. Tvul Yom.
You can't go on הר הבית, Har HaBayis, right. Even on הר
הבית. Har HaBayis. No, טבול יום, Tvul Yom, if you were already
טהור Tahor, then you don't become a טבול יום Tvul Yom by
going to the מקוה. Mikveh, מקוה Mikveh is that you've gone to
the מקוה Mikveh and you're not yet טהור. Tahor, So what basically
the גמרא Gemara is saying here is that the only way this
מצורע Metzora can get up here to use this room is if
he went to the מקוה Mikveh? on day seven and now it's
day eight and he's no longer a טבול יום. Tvul Yom. Then
he's allowed, then he's allowed here, okay? But if he hasn't gone
to the מקוה Mikveh, yesterday, there's no way he's getting here. He
starts off as טמא Tamei and even after going to the מקוה
Mikveh he remains a טבול יום, Tvul Yom, and טבול יום Tvul
Yom is not allowed in that space. Okay, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara says. You cannot say he didn't go to the מקוה
Mikveh? the day before. Okay.
The whole system is dependent upon the integrity of the individual person.
If the person says טהור, Tahor I'm טהור, Tahor if he says
טמא, Tamei, he's טמא. Tamei.
Right,
and that's why we try to make them do these extra things
in order to make sure that they're on their toes. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, אלא אי דלא טבל
הערב
שמש בעי.
Ella ee de-lo taval
ha'er shemesh ba'ei. If he didn't go to the מקוה Mikveh. yet,
he needs to go to the מקוה, Mikveh. wait for it to
be nightfall before he can get into the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim.
אלא אי ודאי דטבל. Ella ee-vada'i de-taval. Fine, he went to the
מקוה Mikveh yesterday. So again, why would רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda demand
to go to the מקוה Mikveh. again today since according to him
it's not a strict requirement of every person, it's really, it's not
like an absolute ritual requirement, it's just to make you remember, and
obviously this guy went the day before. So, so what's the case
where רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would say that מצורעים Metzoraim would go
to the מקוה? Mikveh, So the גמרא Gemara says: הא דאסח דעתיה
הא דלא אסח דעתיה. Ha de-asach da'atei ha de-lo asach da'atei.
If he was, you know, he allowed his mind to wander, he
wasn't being careful after day seven. Day seven he went to the
מקוה, Mikveh very nice. What happened between going to the מקוה Mikva
day seven and showing up in the מקדש Mikdash day eight? Were
you keeping on your toes? Were you focusing on remaining טהור because
you knew you were going to come to the מקוה? Mikva Then
you don't have to go to the מקוה.
Mikva If he slept?
All right, so that's a good question. But presumably, let's say he
was careful about the things around him. It's not touching like dirty
places, it's touching טומאה. Tumah. Okay, he fell on a מת? Meit?
All right, that must be what you're concerned. So if you kept
on your toes from day seven till now, you don't need to
go to the מקוה. Mikva, If you weren't keeping on your toes,
then you have to go to the מקוה Mikva again. Okay, so
that's a very reasonable answer. So גמרא Gemara says, אי אסח דעתיה,
ee asach da'atei, if he stopped paying attention to becoming טמא Tamei
or not, הזאה שלישי ושביעי בעי. hazo'ah shlishi v'shvi'i ba'ei. He'd have
to go, maybe he touched a מת. Meit. Maybe so then if,
then he'd have to go through the, he'd have to do sprinkling
on day three and seven. So you can't just go to the
מקוה. Mikva דאמר רב דוסתאי בר מתון אמר רבי יוחנן היסח הדעת
צריך הזאה שלישי ושביעי. D'amar Rav Dostai bar Masun amar Rebbe Yochanan
Hesach hadat tzarich hazah shlishi v'shvi'i. If somebody isn't paying attention to
what they're touching before they enter the מקדש, Mikdash. they have to
do a whole seven-day preparation process. So basically, it would be like
everybody... so that's a crazy thing. Like now you're like, we know
you've learned before about people that like the חבר Chaver that would
be אוכל חולין בטהרה. ochel chullin be-tahara. Right? So this effectively creates
this system that there's this huge barrier between entering the מקדש Mikdash
unless you're spending every single day, and so so...
unless you're spending every single day
paying attention, hyper-attention to what you're doing and whether you're becoming טמא,
Tamei, you need a seven-day prep... for most normal people, there would
have to be a seven-day preparation period before entering into the מקדש.
Mikdash, Which again, interestingly, like the seven days of the כהן גדול.
Okay, so but that, but that creates this seven-day barrier for most
people. Look at תוספות, Tosafos, by the way: היסח הדעת שלישי ושביעי
בעי. Hesach hadat shlishi v'shvi'i ba'ei.
תוספות Tosafos says, טמא שרץ ונבלה, Tamei sheretz u-nevelah, how about a
guy that touched a dead carcass of an animal? So what do
we say? Go to the מקוה, Mikva come to the מקדש Mikdash,
the next day. So תוספות Tosafos says, why doesn't he have to
wait for seven days? גמרא Gemara says, כל הני דלא צריכין הזאה
שלישי ושביעי צריך לומר כגון דלא אסחו דעתייהו. kol hanei de-lo tzrichin
hazah shlishi v'shvi'i tzarich lomar kigon de-lo asach da'atayihu. Yeah, I touched
a נבלה, nevelah, but throughout that time even after I was טמא
Tamei after touching a נבלה, nevelah, I was being careful that I,
you know, focusing on at least not touching a dead body. So
you basically in order to come to the מקוה Mikva without needing
a seven-day purification process, you have to say that since the last
time, sort of, you know, that I was טהור or whatever, I
have been consistently conscious of not coming in contact
with... אלא, Ella, so again, I don't know why it can't give
the answer that there was a הסח הדעת Hessach Daas from other
טומאות Tumahs but not a הסח הדעת Hessach Daas from מת. Mes.
Right, you could imagine that. Like okay, I'm still staying careful that
I'm not touching a מת Mes but maybe I'm not being careful
about other things, you know. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't like that.
That which seemed to be a very reasonable answer, yes you went
yesterday but maybe you weren't on your toes. The גמרא Gemara rejects
that. So what's the difference, when does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say
a מצורע Metzora goes to the מקוה Mikva, on day eight when
not? So the גמרא says like this, אלא אידי ואידי דלא אסח
דעתיה. Ella, idi v'idi d'lo assach daatei. Fine,
neither of those did you stop paying attention, because then you'd have
to do a seven-day period. So why would he have to go
to the מקוה Mikva again on day eight? לא קשיא הא דטבל
לדעת ביאת מקדש הא דלא טבל לדעת ביאת מקדש. Lo kashya, ha
d'taval l'daas bias Mikdash, ha d'lo taval l'daas bias Mikdash. When he
went because when he went on day seven, was he thinking, "Ah,
I'm going to the מקוה Mikva now and I know that tomorrow
I'm going to be entering into the בית המקדש" or was he
not? Because he's going to be more careful. Right, if the whole
point is is that it makes you stop and reflect and think,
did I become טמא tamei in any other way? Because this מצורע,
Metzora, maybe he also touched a corpse of an animal, maybe there's
other טומאות tumahs or whatever. So if he went to the מקוה,
Mikva, maybe he touched a dead body, right? If he went to
the מקוה Mikva knowing he was going to enter the מקדש, Mikdash
that counts, that's then help, that works for the טבילה before the
מקדש, Mikdash that'll make him remember. If he wasn't thinking about it,
then it doesn't count. Let's say, let's say according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda a guy shows up at the מקדש Mikdash and says,
"Yeah, yesterday I went to the מקוה because I go to the,
I'm a חסיד, chassid, I go to the מקוה every morning." Would
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say fine, you don't have to go? No.
What you do outside of the מקדש Mikdash does not create that
sense of awareness and heightened focus that going to the מקוה in
the process of entering the מקדש Mikdash will do.
So it makes the מקוה, he didn't טובל, tovel he
was טובל tovel on day seven, but if you, if you were
טובל with the mindset that you're going to be entering the מקדש
Mikdash tomorrow, then that'll count. But if you weren't with that mindset,
then you'll do it again when you come to the מקדש Mikdash,
today on day eight.
But then you need שלישי ושביעי shelishi v'shevi'i if you
weren't, no, no, no, you're careful not to touch טומאה, tumah, but
you weren't paying attention to the fact that you were going to
enter the מקדש Mikdash, tomorrow.
And that makes a difference because,
because going, if you're focusing on not touching טומאה, tumah, we're not
afraid you touched the מת. mes. But if you did not, if
if you're going to the מקוה with not with the mindset of
entering the מקדש, Mikdash. it won't help you remember things that might
have occurred in the past.
But that's not considered הסח הדעת. hessach hadaas.
No, that's not הסח הדעת, hessach hadaas, yes.
But doesn't a מצורע Metzora specifically need when he goes to the
מקוה on the seventh day that he has to go to the
מקדש, Mikdash,
yes, the question is are you thinking about it at the time?
And are you thinking about, "Oh yes, I'm going to the מקוה,
yes, and you know, and this would be, and I have to
get ready because tomorrow I'm going into the מקדש." Mikdash, You might
not be necessarily thinking about that, I don't know, in the whole
process. Maybe actually needs to look, you could also say formally, in
order to label it the טבילה before the מקדש, Mikdash you have
to be thinking, "this is the טבילה that's gonna let me go
into the מקדש," Mikdash, that's a more formal explanation. In order to
label it as that one, he has to be specifically consciously identifying
it as such. Let's move on. I got, I've got to end
it at a quarter after so let's move on. Okay, so that's
one answer. One answer is yes, it could work the day before,
but only if that's in your mindset.
ואיבעית אימא Ve-iba'is eima and if you want, תני Tanni when רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that מצורעים Metzora'im and not only מצורעים Metzora'im
went, which implies מצורעים Metzora'im did go, which was a question. So
just switch the גרסא girsa a little bit. תני לא מצורעים אמרו,
Tanni, lo metzora'im amru, no, מצורעים Metzora'im didn't go there, אלא כל
אדם, ella kol adam, other, you know, normal people went there. So
take out the word בלבד. bilvad. Take out the word בלבד. So
Michael says so why is it called לשכת מצורעים? Lishkas Metzora'im? So
could be, so this says maybe initially it was made for the
מצורעים Metzora'im but well according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda why was
it even initially have been made for that? Maybe he denies the
idea that it was called לשכת מצורעים, Lishkas Metzora'im, we've had those
types of debates before. Okay, so the second answer is he completely
rejects it. But now we have a נפקא מינה nafka mina between
the two models. According to בן זומא, I don't care if they
went yesterday, everybody goes on the day as we learn from the
כהן גדול, you go before you enter. And according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that it's about making you sort of be aware about
what's going on, it's possible if you went the day before and
you were keeping that in your mindset that you were gonna go
to the מקדש that that could count and that's the issue of
the מצורע. Metzora. And that's why he might deny that a מצורע
Metzora goes to the מקוה on day eight in the מקדש, okay,
or maybe it depends what he was thinking the day before. Okay,
so now let's take a look. רבינא אמר רבי יהודה ולדבריהם דרבנן
קאמר להו. Ravina amar Rabbi Yehuda, u'l'divreihem d'rabbanan ka'amar lehu. And here's
another variation of that answer. He's responding back to the Rabbis' position.
לדידי, L'didi, as far as I'm concerned, מצורע אין צריך טבילה. Metzora
ein tzarich tevillah. The מצורע Metzora would not even go on day
eight and מצורעים Metzora'im would not use this room. לדידכו, L'did'chu, according
to you, that that a מצורע Metzora would go on day eight,
fine, I get why the מצורעים Metzora'im use this room. But הודו
לי מיהת odu li mi'at at least admit to me דלא מצורעים
בלבד אמרו d'lo metzora'im bilvad amru that it's not limited to מצורעים
Metzora'im אלא כל אדם ella kol adam that any person goes into
this room. Okay, so basically When he said not only מצורעים *Metzoraim*,
it's another way of saying he didn't mean it. For him מצורעים
*Metzoraim* wouldn't go, but he's saying normal people have to use the
מקוה *Mikveh* as well. ורבנן *Verabbanan*, and the Rabbis would say back,
מצורע דייש בטומאה *Metzora da'ish betuma*. A מצורע *Metzora* is like trampling
through טומאה *tuma*. A מצורע *Metzora* is immersed in טומאה *tuma*. So
he, we will make go into the room, because he, here we're
afraid that even on day eight, you know, he needs another reminder.
כל אדם לא דייש בטומאה *Kol adam lo da'ish betuma*, a normal
person does not trample through טומאה *tuma*, which means that according to
this גמרא *Gemara*, this גמרא *Gemara* seems to present, although there's a
little debate of רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafos*, a third radical opinion,
that there's a רבנן *Rabbanan* that deny that you normally have to
go to the מקוה *Mikveh* before and before entering into the מקדש
*Mikdash*. They say the only people that would use this מקוה *Mikveh*
would be the מצורעים *Metzoraim*. Yes, he went day before, he has
to go again. He's completely in a whole state of טומאה *tuma*,
we don't know, he needs he needs to be reminded, okay, but
a normal person does not need to go. If you, you know,
we trust that you became טהור *tahor*, that you thought it through,
that if you're here, you know that you're טהור *tahor*, and there's
not a ritual demand that everybody go the day before. So the
only people who would go to the מקוה *Mikveh*, use the מקוה
*Mikveh* in that space, would be מצורעים *Metzoraim*. So now we have
three opinions. One is בן זומא *Ben Zoma* that every person has
to do it based on the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. The other
is רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, do it to remind you that you
might be טמא *tamei*, and therefore it's possible if you did it
the day before it's okay. And the רבנן *Rabbanan* here, who argue
on רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, that seems to say that actually only
מצורעים *Metzoraim* have to do it. Normal people don't have to do
it. Obviously they have to be טהור *tahor*, but they don't have
to go to the מקוה *Mikveh* the day before. Okay, תוספות *Tosafos*
tries to...
You went to the מקוה *Mikveh* a week ago and you're okay
since you
didn't, you watched yourself since then. Yeah, exactly, obviously you have to
be טהור *tahor*, but you don't have to go the day before.
Okay. So that's a radical third opinion. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף
*Amlei Abaye le-Rav Yosef*, so אביי *Abaye* said to רב יוסף *Rav
Yosef*, נימא רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי יהודה כבן זומא סבירא להו *neima
Rabbanan de-pligi alei de-Rabbi Yehuda ke-Ben Zoma sevira lehu*. Let's say the
Rabbis that argue on רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* hold that argue on
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
and say that and say that... Now רש"י *Rashi* says we're going
back to the earlier ones where the question was whether the Rabbis
said that a מצורע *Metzora* goes on day eight, everybody including a
מצורע *Metzora* goes on day eight, and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* said,
no, מצורע *Metzora* doesn't have to go, he went the day before.
So what would be the reason for the idea that the מצורע
*Metzora* would go again on day eight? So maybe that's because they
hold like בן זומא *Ben Zoma*. And therefore everybody goes on when
they enter in. והאי דקתני מצורע *Ve-hai de-katani Metzora*, and the fact
that they said a מצורע *Metzora* goes on day eight, להודיעך כחו
דרבי יהודה *le-odi'ach kocho de-Rabbi Yehuda*, to tell you the חידוש *chiddush*
that according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* מצורע *Metzora* doesn't go on
day eight. But really, when the Rabbis said that a מצורע *Metzora*
goes on day eight, they really, they really don't mean to deny
that everybody goes. Of course everybody goes, like בן זומא *Ben Zoma*,
everybody goes the day before. It's just also the מצורע *Metzora*, and
to contrast it to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* who says a מצורע
*Metzora* doesn't go because he went the day before. או דלמא *O
dilma*, or do we say, שאני מצורע דדייש בטומאה *shani Metzora de-da'ish
betuma*, maybe like we just said before, like we just said, that
the Rabbis actually are saying that nobody goes the day before... when
they come to the מקדש *Mikdash*. The only person that goes is
the מצורע *Metzora*. ואמר ליה *Ve-amar lei*, שאני מצורע דדייש בטומאה *shani
Metzora de-da'ish betuma*, yes, they're saying the more radical point, that the
only person who goes is the מצורע *Metzora* because he's immersed in
טומאה *tuma*. So the גמרא *Gemara* tries to pull back. The גמרא
*Gemara* tries to say when the Rabbis say the מצורעים *Metzoraim* go,
they're not necessarily denying that a normal person goes.
Okay, everybody with me, right? We have the Rabbis that say מצורע
*Metzora* goes on day eight. What do they think about a normal
person? So so now we're trying to say, you know, maybe they
hold like בן זומא *Ben Zoma*, everybody goes the day they enter,
including a מצורע *Metzora*, they're not דוקא *davka* מצורע *Metzora*. Okay, and
then we would only have two opinions, one opinion everybody goes when
they enter and the other is you go to remind you, so
maybe a מצורע *Metzora* doesn't. But the גמרא *Gemara* says no, I'm
going, we're going to say there's a third opinion here, that what
the Rabbis are actually saying is that normal persons do not go.
The only person that goes to the מקוה *Mikveh* before entering is
the מצורע *Metzora*. Okay, someone is going to do an עבודה *avoda*,
right? Well we'll see about that, why the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
doesn't. Okay, we'll get to that according to to that issue. But
a normal person does not go, only the מצורע *Metzora* who was
immersed in טומאה *tuma* prior to this period, and therefore we have
really three opinions, and we will continue with this tomorrow.